today we are going to talk about svet
svelt is a tool to build interactive
websites that was chosen as the most
loved web framework in last year's stack
overflow developer survey so today we
are going to find out what is and how
does svelt work what makes it different
from react what makes it faster than
react what makes people like it so much
and who should learn it we will also
take a look at how does his belt code
look like by making a couple of tiny
examples let's get started as i said
svelt is a tool that helps you make
interactive websites just like react
does but it does it in a very different
way unlike react.js or vjs as veldt is
not really a library or a framework
zvelt is more like a compiler which
makes it very very different from its
competition if we build our applications
using react for example after we finish
the application and we publish it to the
word when a user comes to our website
they will have to download two pieces of
code the first one is the code that we
wrote all the logic that makes up our
application the second code is a copy of
the react.js code this is because the
code that we wrote uses react.js so it
makes sense that to be able to run our
application our users are going to need
to download react as well react is not
alone in this this is like a standard
practice for example if you use jquery
in your code the user is going to have
to also download the jquery so they can
be able to run your code which makes
sense but this is not what's belt thus
when i first tried svelt long time ago
and they had the version one of their
website they were marketing svelte as
the magic ui framework that disappears
this is because it kind of does it sort
of disappears after you write your
application using svet and when you are
ready to publish it to the word svelte
analyzes and compiles or translates your
code into normal javascript code that
the browser will be able to understand
by itself there is no need to explain to
the browser what is belt is this means
that when the user comes to our website
and if we are using svelte we are going
to give to the user only the code
required to make our application run and
we are not going to also give to the
user a framework on top of that this
makes the size of svelte apps to be much
much much smaller than apps created with
react or vue.js
this to-do application implemented in
svelt only weighs 3.6 kilobytes the same
to do application implemented in reality
yes weights more than 45 kilobytes zvelt
applications are also faster than view
and react applications as you can see
here they are almost as fast as raw
vanilla javascript
as this veldt website says svelte is
basically as fast as vanilla js which
makes sense because it is vanilla js
just vanilla that you did not have to
write it's also because of this compiler
dansveld doesn't use something called
virtual dom
virtual dom is a representation of the
ui of your application that react.js
keeps on memory and that is synced from
time to time with the real ui that the
user is looking at and this allows real
gds to find the elements that need to be
refreshed to show the changes in the ui
back when react dds was released keeping
a copy of the ui in memory to check for
state changes was something that no
other frameworks were doing back then
where according to sveld there is no
need to use virtual dom anymore since
the compiler can generate more optimized
javascript code that can refresh the ui
in a faster way i personally don't think
that virtual dom versus no virtual dom
is something we should focus on there
are some frameworks out there that are
faster than svex like for example
inferno and they use virtual dom so
instead let's move on to our next point
why do people like svelte so much i
can't speak for everyone but based on my
own experience between using svelte and
react.js and by reading the comments
online i would say that the biggest
reason for the love is the developer
experience i actually enjoyed working
with svelte compared to react.js or vgs
i can really say that it feels like the
people making veldt actually care about
the developers using svelte they care
about the developer experience which is
super nice to feel also it's very
intuitive and very easy to learn if you
already come from react or view js i
would say the feeling is very similar to
what you might feel if you are a java
developer and you are used to all these
rules and all these concepts and all
those things and then you come to python
and you see the syntax and how clean it
is and how no rules there are to show
you what i mean let's build a tiny click
counter with svelte as well component is
composed of three parts one is the
script tag the other one is the style
tag and below those you can write
whatever html you want if you're a view
developer i am sure that this will look
familiar to you now in the style tag of
course we write the styles of our
components as you can see is pretty
intuitive already we know where to put
our logic we know where to put our
styles we know where to put our html now
it's time for the logic i want to make a
variable that will hold the value of the
amount of clicks and i want to show that
value to the user so we create a normal
javascript variable inside of the script
tag and we also include it in our html
making use of curly braces now i want to
make a function that increases the
number of clicks every time it runs now
we have to say that we want this
function to run every time our user
clicks on the button in our html and we
do this by doing this
and we are done we just built a counter
with svelte as you can see the code is
super easy to read anyone with a basic
level of html css and javascript is
going to understand what is going on and
unlike with react we didn't have to
learn concepts like hooks or state
beforehand to show you what i mean by
nice developer experience let's now
modify our example a little bit to only
allow the user to click one time right
now the user can click an unlimited
amount of time so to fulfill the
requirements we might be inclined to
write some code on the script tag but in
zvelt we don't have to instead we just
add the once event modifier to our
button and just by doing this as veldt
will run the increase click function
just once and never again this is what i
mean when i say nice developer
experiences vent is full of these tiny
little things that will save you time as
a developer another example of these are
bindings they make it super easy for you
to get input from the user to build a
simple hello world with the name of the
user all we have to do is create a
variable on the script tag along with an
input and an h2 and then in our input we
bind or connect which is what binding
sort of means the value of the variable
with the value of the input and that's
it that's how easy it is to capture
input and show it to the user using
svelte as you can see in our example if
the user doesn't write anything on the
input it just says hello in the
exclamation mark it looks kind of weird
why don't we instead hide the text using
if else to add the if else in its belt
all we have to do is this now as you can
see the syntax looks a little bit
different but it's pretty easy to read
as you can see svelt has these tiny
little things like bind or ones that
save us time in doing tasks that we
would usually implement just doing code
by hand in react.js
tasks so common as getting input from
the user as you can see don't take as
much time to build as if it was in react
also as you can see the code is very
readable even for somebody looking at it
for the first time so now it's time to
talk about who should learn svelt i
think that if you are a react.js or a
view developer and you don't really
enjoy your work anymore you're tired of
reality you're tired of you and you want
something more simpler to use and more
different and you want something to
refresh your eyes then i think svelte is
a very good choice if you are already
productive in react.js or vjs i am sure
that just by following the tutorial in
this veldt website which by the way is
an amazing tutorial it will take you
less than a couple of days to feel
productive inspect but if you are a
beginner and you're looking for
something that will give you a job i
think that in this area react gs wins
per week react.js has downloaded more
than 14 million times these compared
with vue.js that is downloaded more than
3 million times
compared with svet that is downloaded
only 200 000 times i'm not saying that
you should learn something because it's
popular what i'm saying is that
sometimes popularity also means a big
community more packages more frameworks
more tools more best practices and more
importantly
more jobs
i think that react is so stable and so
widely used and this is why we have
frameworks now built on top of react
like nextgs and gatsby which are a
complete joy and pleasure to use they
also have super huge communities behind
them and are used by some of the biggest
companies in the world like for example
tick tock web is built using next js
which by the way this just reminds me
that we just finished recording
uploading and subtitling in hangul a
free two and a half hour course in next
js for beginners so if you're wondering
what do i mean when i say next gs is
awesome and so enjoyable to use then
please take that course it's for free
and you are going to find out what makes
nexjs so special that makes developers
and big companies like it and use it so
much this veldt also has its framework
and it's called this belt kit which i
tried and i really liked but it's still
in beta and even though people are
already using it in production this
shows you a little bit about how young
this build community is now as you can
see so far my problems with veldt are
not problems with svelt as a tool i
think the tool is great and i like using
it and as you saw before it makes doing
things very very simple it's good
but my problems are basically with the
context or the point in time where the
tool is all these things can change the
community can grow there can be more
jobs maybe companies will adopt spelt
maybe they're going to be more tutorials
more packages more tooling who knows but
it's also important to remember that the
javascript ecosystem has stabilized a
lot developers have mostly settled down
with their own tools and what they like
and companies also don't really change
libraries or frameworks that often or
almost never but there is something that
sort of bothers me about recommending
svelte for beginners and that is how
magical it is as usual before svelta has
these nice things like ones or bind that
are literal magic or you see that the
way that they handle if and else are
very spelt specific they are not syntax
that we are used to and we have seen
before one of the reasons why i like and
recommend react so much is that by
learning and working with react and the
tools in the ecosystem i became a better
javascript developer overall react in my
opinion has less magic than svelt and i
think that when learning to code magic
can hurt you more than it can help you
for example when showing a list of items
to a user in react you would use a
function called map which is not
specific to react and if you learn it it
will help you everywhere you go in the
javascript world in belt to do the same
thing you will have to write something
like this
which is not ugly i understand it is
very readable and i would say is more
clear than map is and i'm not saying
that one is better than the other but
i'm saying that one is more pure
functional javascript and the other
isn't
and i personally prefer to be as close
to the language as possible i feel like
if the tools that we use are again as
close to the language as possible if
that tool that we are using goes away
tomorrow we are not going to lose as
much knowledge as we would do if we
learn specific syntax if we learn
specific magic tricks and then if that
tool goes away all that is lost picasso
said that you have to learn the rules
like a pro so you can break them like an
artist now he clearly learned the rules
like a pro if you look at some of his
early work you can tell that he knew the
rules very very well i feel like
react.js is a tool that puts food on the
table and i really feel like svelte is
art i just don't think that beginners
should start with svelte
i feel like we have to learn the rules
first so then we can break them now i
know what you think on the comments let
me know what are your opinions on zvelt
have you seen it before have you tried
it was this the first time are you
curious are you going to look into it
let me know everything i want to know
i'm going to be reading the comments
right now thank you as always for
watching this video and don't forget if
you want to learn next gs and see why so
many people like nextgs including this
guy right here then please check the
link on the description it's a free two
hour and a half next js course that's
going to show you the best and most
shiny parts about this awesome framework
thank you for watching stay happy stay
free eat kimchi come see me
stay healthy bye